<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The narrative and case of Simson Tonge, Gent. being a true account delivered upon oath before Mr. Justice Bridgeman, in the presence of Dr. Titus Oates, relating to Capt. Sam. Ely, Monsieur Choqueux, &amp;c. and my self, who would have induced me to swear that my father and Dr. Oates, were the contrivers of the horrid Popish Plot, with other material passages omitted in the affidavit, together with some short reflections upon Mr. Le'estranges [sic] dialogue between Zekiel and Ephraim : humbly tendered to the consideration of the Honourable House of Commons.</title>
            <author>Tonge, Simson, b. 1656 or 7.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62928</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1884A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16796</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12599464</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12599464</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64123</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62928)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64123)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 676:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The narrative and case of Simson Tonge, Gent. being a true account delivered upon oath before Mr. Justice Bridgeman, in the presence of Dr. Titus Oates, relating to Capt. Sam. Ely, Monsieur Choqueux, &amp;c. and my self, who would have induced me to swear that my father and Dr. Oates, were the contrivers of the horrid Popish Plot, with other material passages omitted in the affidavit, together with some short reflections upon Mr. Le'estranges [sic] dialogue between Zekiel and Ephraim : humbly tendered to the consideration of the Honourable House of Commons.</title>
                  <author>Tonge, Simson, b. 1656 or 7.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for C.W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published for the satisfaction of all true Protestants."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tonge, Simson, b. 1656 or 7.</term>
               <term>L'Estrange, Roger, --  Sir, 1616-1704.</term>
               <term>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</term>
               <term>Ely, Samuel.</term>
               <term>Choqueux, Anthony.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:64123:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
THE NARRATIVE AND CASE OF Simſon Tonge, Gent.</p>
            <p>BEING A true Account delivered upon Oath before Mr. Juſtice <hi>Bridgeman,</hi> in the preſence of Dr. <hi>Titus Oates,</hi> relating to Capt. <hi>Sam. Ely, Monſieur Choqueux, &amp;c.</hi> and my ſelf, who would have induced me to ſwear that my Father and Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> were the Contrivers of the Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Popish Plot, with other material Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges omitted in the Affidavit, together with ſome short Reflections upon Mr. <hi>Le'eſtranges</hi> Dialogue between ZEKIEL and EPHRAIM.</p>
            <p>HUMBLY Tendered to the Conſideration of the Honorable Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the Satisfaction of all True Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>c. W.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:64123:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64123:2"/>
            <head>To the Candid READER.</head>
            <p>BEing ordered to come to my Tryal this laſt Term, but finding it to be defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for ſome longer time, is the reaſon why I have publiſht my Caſe, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed that ſome of thoſe Perſons with whom I was concerned are gone, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly Mr. <hi>L'eſtrange,</hi> and likewiſe that Captain <hi>Ely</hi> has abſented himſelf, who is one of the principal Abettors in my Buſineſs, and therefore is particularly mentioned with me, in the Information which is Fil'd againſt me on the Crown Side.</p>
            <p>An other Reaſon which induced me to Print my Caſe is, that though very few do underſtand it, yet every one thinks himſelf a competent Judge, and with a clamorous Noiſe (common to the Rabble eſpecially,) exclaiming againſt me, becauſe my Father is concerned in this Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair; which therefore in all Perſons Opinions renders me the more contemptible; I muſt lay my Hand on my Mouth, and confeſs, it is a thing very unnatural, and contrary to the Laws of God and Nature, which the very Heathens did abhor, that a Son ſhould ſeek to ruine his own Parent, who gave him being; Being a Crime of a very black and deformed Aſpect, but hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it is commonly reported, that I ſhould ſwear againſt my Father to take away his Life, it is as Falſe as God is True, who ever was the Author of that lying Rumor; and though my Information upon which I was committed to <hi>Newgate,</hi> was drawn up in theſe Words, For high Miſdemeanours, and indeavouring by falſe Accuſations, and Subornation of Perjury to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame the Kings Evidence, and all the Proſecution of the Popiſh Plot<hi>:</hi> Yet no ſuch thing as Perjury can be proved againſt me, as I hope will apparently appear, by the peruſal of theſe Sheets, in the caſe of <hi>L'Eſtrange,</hi> who would willingly have ſworn me to the Objections I drew up againſt the Plot; But I would not conſent to it<hi>:</hi> But the great Reaſon why I was prevailed upon to write thoſe Objections was this, that <hi>Ely</hi> having a very wheedling and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Tongue, and finding me all along very tender of my Fathers Safety, (a Duty incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent on all Children) and when ever I mentioned him, with many deep Oaths, and ſolemn Aſſeverations aſſured me, that my Father ſhould not receive any the leaſt Dammage by what I did; and to uſe his own Expreſſion (which I have heard him more than once Repeat) that a hair of his Head ſhould not be hurt, this was the Argument which ingulpht me in this <hi>Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi> and Pit of Trouble; and though I do not deſire to palliate my Crime, yet I hope this Information will give ſome Satisfaction to all ſuch Perſons as have had no true account of it; that as it is my great Trouble, ſo it has been my Misfortune, to fall into the Hands of wicked Perſons, who through their Deluſions and Inſtigations, did perſwade me to ruine not only my ſelf, but (that which is more deplorable) likewiſe my innocent Relations; and this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Logick, under the ſpecious Title of undeceiving the Kingdom, as to the truth of the Plot; and whilſt that I am confin'd to a Priſon (which is a kind of a living Death) I hope the Truth will be ſought into; that thoſe who have been my Abettors, will not be ſuffered to eſcape Unpuniſht, having made an ingenuous and full Confeſſion, deſirous ever ſince I was firſt ſummon'd to appear before the Councel, to diſcover the Truth; whom I have here diſplayed in her naked Simplicity, without the affectation of good Language, or the flour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhes of Rhetorick; being likewiſe very conſcientious in the Relation; which I do not queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will be very acceptable to all Perſons who love upright and plain dealing<hi>:</hi> and though an indelible Character may be branded on me, for being ſo undutiful to my Father; Yet I make no doubt that when my Caſe is weighed in the impartial Ballance of an unbiaſt Judgment,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64123:3"/>
(though I do not expect to acquit my ſelf from being culpable) yet I ſay I do not diſpair, but thoſe very Perſons who have moſt accuſed me, will paſs more favourable Cenſures, on my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious undertaking againſt the Kings Evidence, and though I may be condemn'd for a great Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain, yet withal they will commiſerate my Condition, for hark'ning to ſuch evil Councellors: for as that Wit is accounted beſt which is dear bought, ſo it will make me more careful for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to hearken to the like Advice; who have ſadly found that Maxime true, <hi>Quae ſupra nos, nihil ad nos,</hi> for young men as they are too ſoon prevailed upon to act thoſe things which often prove very prejudicial to them, and their Friends, for want of Judgment, and through inadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency, being wholly unexperienced as to the things of this World; ſo when they imbrace good Counſel, and leave off thoſe ways, it merits Commendation: for it is the purſuit of an evil Action, which aggravates the Crime, and renders it the more odious, which Fault muſt be left to the Law to determine; for where I am guilty, as it will be to no purpoſe to make any Apology for my ſelf; ſo where I am innocent my own Conſcience will acquit me from the malevolent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of evil Men.</p>
            <q>Da veniam ſubitis, non diſplicuiſſe meretur, Feſtinat Patriae qui placuiſſe ſuae.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Kings Bench December,</hi> 13. 1681.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>L' Eſtranges</hi> Caſe coming to my Hands, which he calls a civil Dialogue betwixt <hi>Zekil</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim;</hi> and finding ſeveral palpable Lyes in it, which he endeavours to throw upon the World relating to my Buſineſs; I thought I was bound in Conſcience to vindicate my ſelf, and to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the World, by a publick and ingenuous Acknowledgment, relating to thoſe Perſons with whom it has been my misfortune to be concern'd; that when my Caſe is candidly laid down, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly they will cenſure; and that they will not pin their Faith upon the credibility of <hi>L'-Eſtranges</hi> Writings; who though he may paſs for a man of Wit, and has ſlipt his Neck out of the Collar, cannot boaſt much of his Honeſty or Loyalty, notwithſtanding all his fine Flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in his Appeal, and other Pamphlets; for certainly if any Perſon make it his Buſineſs and Study to pick holes in the Kings Evidence, theſe things are inconſiſtent with the Loyalty of his Soveraign, and the good of the Proteſtant Religion, of which with ſo many Oaths and ſolemn Imprecations, he tells us he is a zealous Profeſſor; but now after all fearing to be ſeverely hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Hands of Juſtice, he is fairly fled for't, which in his Appeal he calls the ſeeking of an other World, where I ſhall leave him to that Beloved Repoſe, which he tells us he has long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired; being as weary of the World, as Peeviſhneſs it ſelf can be of him, where I ſhall leave him be it where it will, in his ſo much beloved <hi>Elizium,</hi> and give you a true and impartial account of all the Tranſactions which have paſt betwixt Captain <hi>Ely, Monſieur Choquveux, &amp;c.</hi> and my ſelf.</p>
            <p>About the Month of <hi>May</hi> laſt, my Father did remove out of the Lodgings which he had in <hi>Whitehal,</hi> into the City, and I then lodged with one Mr. <hi>King,</hi> in <hi>Shandoys</hi> Street, and being out of all Employment, not knowing well how to ſpend my time, having formerly lodged with one Mrs. <hi>Lane,</hi> I frequently went to her Houſe, which was to my beſt remembrance about <hi>June</hi> or <hi>July</hi> laſt, where the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Lane</hi> did often ask me what news there was, and what was become of the Popiſh Plot; and ſhe ſaid that it was now apparent to all the World, that the Plot was contrived by the Presbyterians, that her Husband was wrongfully turned out of his Place, and that her Son <hi>Lane</hi> in the Kings Bench was Fined and Pillory'd for ſpeaking the Truth; but ſhe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to ſee that day, when the Truth would be found out, and that ſhe ſhould live to ſee Doctor <hi>Oates,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bedloe</hi> hanged; for they had only been the diſturbers of the Nation, inſtead of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Preſervers of it: with ſuch like railing and impudent Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>About the midſt of <hi>June</hi> or <hi>July</hi> going about ſome Buſineſs to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall, I met old Mr. <hi>Lane,</hi> who deſired me to go to his Houſe, which I did, and there entring into diſcourſe with Mrs. <hi>Lane,</hi> ſhe told me amongſt other Diſcourſe, which I cannot well remember, that ſhe had ſomething to ſay to me, which might make my Fortune for ever, and that no Perſon was ſo fit to do what ſhe ſhould propoſe as my ſelf; I asked her, what that was, for having been for ſome conſiderable time out of all manner of Employment; I ſhould be very willing and ready to imbrace any honeſt way to get a Livelihood: Then ſhe replied Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> if you will draw up ſome Objections againſt the Plot, you need not fear ſufficient Encouragement, for I can procure ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Perſons that will ſtand by you; and I know a particular Friend one Captain <hi>Ely,</hi> which is a Perſon of very great Intereſt at Court, who will introduce you to the ſpeech of the King; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you may be tender of your Fathers welfare, he being involved with Doctor Oates, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64123:3"/>
likely to be mentioned with him in your Papers; I will procure your Fathers Pardon, by the means of Captain <hi>Ely,</hi> for truly I did once look upon your Father, to be a very honeſt Man, but now I am of the contrary Opinion, ſince I am told he is in his Writings ſo bitter againſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts; but notwithſtanding I verily believe, he was meerly drawn in by Doctor <hi>Oates;</hi> ſo that your Father being innocent, it will be very eaſie to get his Pardon; upon which I repli'd I did not know any thing of the Plot, Mrs. <hi>Lane</hi> anſwered that having written ſo many things for my Father, I could not be ſo ſtupid but I could raiſe ſome Objections out of thoſe Papers, which if I would do, ſhe would give me what Aſſiſtance lay in her Power; after which Diſcourſe I went to my Lodging, ſhe having appointed me to come and ſee her again, as ſoon as I could, and then ſhe would give me a farther Account of her Sentiments concerning that Buſineſs.</p>
            <p>I came not near her Houſe a good while after, but her Husband having got knowledg of my Lodging, came to me and ſaid, that his Wife had been ſeveral times to ſeek Captain <hi>Ely,</hi> but could not find him; but now ſhe had found him out, and that he promiſed to be at her Houſe that Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and deſired me to go along with him, which at his importuning of me I did, and Mrs. <hi>Lane</hi> told me ſhe had found out Captain <hi>Ely,</hi> who was very glad and willing to embrace the Offer; and had promiſed her to come, which <hi>Ely</hi> did, and calling for Drink fell into Diſcourſe with me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my Condition, and how I lived; I told him my Condition was not very plentiful, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied God help you, and if I would take his Advice, I might quickly raiſe my Fortune; and ſaid like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, come Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> you are an ingenious young Man, and I am perſwaded you know a great deal of this Plot, I mean as to the truth of it, as for my own particular part, at firſt I did believe this Plot, and thought thus with my ſelf when I heard that there was a Plot diſcovered to his Majeſty: God has been pleaſed to make theſe Perſons very Inſtrumental for the good of theſe Kingdoms; and therefore they ought to be encouraged and rewarded according to the Merit of ſuch Services; but when I did afterward ſeriouſly conſider what the Perſons were which pretended to diſcover it; being moſt of them Perſons of profligate Life, I was then quite of an other mind; and now I am ſo far from being of my former Opinion, that I do no more believe the Plot, that none being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent but you and I in this Room, any one ſhould endeavour to perſwade me that there are a thouſand Perſons in company with us; and withal deſired me according to Mrs. <hi>Lanes</hi> firſt requeſt that I would draw up ſome Objections againſt the Plot. I told him I was Ignorant of any Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions of the Plot, only that my Father brought Doctor <hi>Oates</hi> into the Councel; upon which <hi>Ely</hi> replied that was nothing to the Purpoſe, all the World knew that, but if I brought any thing which might ſtand as an Objection againſt the Plot, it muſt be matter of Fact that muſt do the buſineſs; and ſomething of Falſhood and Contrivance muſt be proved to have been betwixt my Father and Doctor <hi>Oates,</hi> and that theſe muſt be the meaſures I muſt take to overthrow the Kings Evidence, and was very importunate with me to draw up ſome ſuch Papers, and told me he would meet me again at the ſame place the next Day.</p>
            <p>I having ſome Buſineſs at <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> at my return called at Mrs. <hi>Lanes</hi> Houſe, expecting <hi>Elys</hi> coming; but miſſing of him I went away in the Evening, and having drawn up a Paper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very much troubled in my Mind; I went to a Perſon whoſe Name I cannot remember, but was by his Profeſſion a Tallow-Chandler, and was before the Councel, the firſt time that I was Summoned to appear before the right Honourable Board. I read that Paper to this Perſon, who as ſoon as he had heard it, told me, Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> this is a very dangerous Paper, and may prove of ill Conſequence to you, and therefore as a Friend I would adviſe you to burn it, and whoever thoſe Perſons are who have adviſed you to this, they intend to ruine you, go near them no more, and I took his Advice, and burnt it, fully reſolving never to concern my ſelf any more with <hi>Ely,</hi> and abſented my ſelf above a fortnight from Mrs. <hi>Lanes</hi> Houſe; during my abſence old Mr. <hi>Lane</hi> and his Wife had been upon the hunt to ſeek me, but could not find me; but old Mr. <hi>Lane</hi> having been very diligent in his Enquiry, heard where I was, and went and told his Wife, who came in great haſt to me, and ſaid that Captain <hi>Ely</hi> had been twice at her Houſe, and was much troubled that I did not come; that ſhe had left him at her Houſe; I replied I did not care for concerning my ſelf with <hi>Ely,</hi> then ſaid ſhe you will never have the like Opportunity, to make your Fortune, therefore be Couragious, for you have the beſt man (except one) in <hi>England</hi> on your ſide; and was very importunate with me to write out ſome Objections againſt the Plot. I told her I had written ſome out already, but they were burnt<hi>!</hi> Nay ſaid ſhe if you falter thus at the beginning you will never do no good on't. I told her I hoped as ſhe pretended to be my Friend, ſhe would not deſire me to act any thing againſt my Conſcience; then ſhe asked me if I had any Money, I told her no, ſays ſhe I am but a poor Woman, yet here is a Shilling for you, and doubt not but you ſhall have Encouragement enough; ſo ſhe made me promiſe her before ſhe left me, that I would draw up that Paper again, and come after her to her Houſe where <hi>Ely</hi> expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:64123:4"/>
That Evening I came to Mrs. <hi>Lanes</hi> Houſe, and there I found <hi>Ely,</hi> who ſaid Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> I am glad to ſee you, have you drawn up that Paper, which you promiſed me? I told him I had, and gave it to him; <hi>Ely</hi> read it over, and ſmiling ſaid Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> this will do very well, but you muſt put your name to it, which I did, and afterwards <hi>Ely</hi> ſigned it, and to my beſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance old Mr. <hi>Lane</hi> and his Daughter likewiſe ſigned it, as being Witneſſes; now ſays <hi>Ely</hi> you have no reaſon to be afraid, for you have done no more, than I do my ſelf, and as he was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away with the Paper, told me he would ſee me within two or three days, but he muſt firſt go to carry that Paper to the King, who was then at <hi>Windſore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Towards the end of <hi>July,</hi> or the beginning of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> comes old <hi>Lane</hi> to my Lodging, and told me that <hi>Ely</hi> had ſent to his Houſe, and told me that I muſt go and ſpeak with the King, and that I muſt go to <hi>Ely</hi>'s Houſe in <hi>Holborne:</hi> when I came thither, <hi>Ely</hi> told me he had hired a Coach for himſelf, and me to go to <hi>Windſore;</hi> that I muſt go and ſpeak with his Majeſty, and ſaid he had proffered a Guinny for a pair of Oares, but could not have it; I went along with him to <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore,</hi> and as we were near the Town, <hi>Ely</hi> ſaid now Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> you are going to ſpeak with the King, pray recollect your Memory, and ſay ſomething that may give the King Satisfaction, for his Majeſty believes you know a great deal concerning the Plot, and be ſure remember to beg your Fathers Pardon, for I find you are very tender of his Safety; and I told him he might aſſure himſelf I ſhould not forget to do that; ſo ſoon as we came to <hi>Windſore, Ely</hi> brought me to the <hi>Garter</hi> Tavern, and went immediately to find out Mr. <hi>Chiffins,</hi> where having had the Honour to kiſs the Kings Hand, his Majeſty was pleaſed to ask me ſeveral Queſtions not convenient to be related, and when I came from the King, I walked for ſome time in the next Room with Mr. <hi>Chiffins:</hi> who ſaid I did very well to diſcover it, if I knew any thing of the Plot, for a clear Conſcience was the moſt excellent thing in the World; then <hi>Ely</hi> and my ſelf came away toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and I askt him what Diſcourſe he had with the King, he ſaid it was nothing relating to my Buſineſs; but concerning ſome Forreſt Affairs, and he carried me from the <hi>Caſtle</hi> to the <hi>Garter</hi> Tavern, where after we had drunk ſeveral Bottles of Wine (for by the way you muſt take this Note, when <hi>Ely</hi> had once ingaged me in the Buſineſs, I was ſeldome very ſober) he told me he thought I ſpoke as if I was afraid; I replied, the ſight of his Majeſty would daunt any Perſon; however ſays he be couragious, and ſtick to what you have done, and let me alone to manage the Intrigue: and then began ſeveral Healths to the Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> and made me pledg him; then he told me he had given me nothing yet to encourage me, and gave me a Guinny, which he ſaid was only an Earneſt, intending ſhortly to make it up a much bigger Sum, before I was many days older; while we were drinking, there came in a ſtranger to us, who told me he heard I was upon a very good Deſign, that he for his part did heartily pray, that God would aſſiſt and direct me, and that there was no doubt to be made of it, but all good Catholiques, would likewiſe unanimouſly joyn with him in it, who did deſire the truth of the Plot to be found out; and having drunk two or three Bottles of Wine with us, he took his leave, then <hi>Ely</hi> told me that Perſon was a <hi>Portugueſe,</hi> and had been the Queens Cook a long time; and is a very honeſt man, otherwiſe, I would not have made him privy to our Concerns; for Secrecy is now very convenient, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leſt I ſhould be diſcovered by my own Name, he would call me always Mr. <hi>Hudibras;</hi> and the next day I ſhould go with him to <hi>London,</hi> and when I came thither he called a Hackney Coach, and carried me to his own Houſe in <hi>Holborne;</hi> and leſt notice ſhould be taken of me, he thought it would be very convenient for me to remove my ſelf to ſome private Lodging near himſelf; to which I replied, Captain I cannot conveniently do that; for Mr. <hi>King</hi> with whom I Lodge is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry civil honeſt Man, and I have not paid him for my Diet nor Lodging; and I ſhould be thought very rude to go away and leave him, without giving him the leaſt notice; ſays he do not trouble your head for that, give me an account what you owe him, or any other Perſons about the Town and I will ſee it paid; ſo I gave him an Account of ſeveral Sums of Money which I owed, and then he deſired his Wife to look me out a Lodging, which ſhe did and brought me to a Smiths Shop in <hi>Lyon</hi> Street near <hi>Bloomsbury,</hi> where I had not continued long, but my Uncle found me out, and ſent his Man to ſpeak with me, who told me that by a no leſs than miraculous Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence he was informed of the wicked Deſign I was going about, and asked me what kind of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it was with whom I was concerned, I ſaid he went by the name of Captain <hi>Ely,</hi> and was a very remarkable Perſon, for he had a great red Scar down his Noſe, and my Uncle ſaid he knew him, and that he was a great Raſcal, and lived by cheating and ſharking about the Town, and therefore not unworthily called by ſome Captain Bounce, my Uncle adviſed me to be ingenuous with him, and to give him a true account, whatſoever had paſt betwixt <hi>Ely</hi> and me; which I did under my own hand, and my Uncle adviſed me to have a care of forſewaring myſelf, and what a grievous Sin Perjury was, that what I went about was very unnatural, being againſt my own Father. I ſaid I was heartily ſorry for what I had done, and was willing to diſcover whatever I knew, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64123:4"/>
ſent ſeveral Letters to him, of what had paſt between us from time to time; yet <hi>Ely</hi> ſome way or other got notice, that I kept Correſpondence with my Uncle, and was very jealous of me, and went to enquire what Perſons came to ſpeak with me, and the people where I lodged having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed him that ſeveral Perſons had been there to inquire for me; ſaid, Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> you do very ill in thus diſcovering your Lodging, and if you intend that this buſineſs ſhall ever come to any perfection, pray keep your ſelf private from all manner of Company, except thoſe who I know you may confide in, otherwiſe you ſpoyl all, for ſuch Intrigues as theſe are, muſt be manag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a great deal of Prudence, for we have a great many Eyes over us; and after Dinner ſent me for my Linnen, which I left at my Lodging in <hi>Shandoys</hi> Street, and ſent his Wife to pay what I owed there, and removed me in the Evening to one Mrs. <hi>Nichols</hi> Houſe in <hi>Ollivers</hi> Ally in the <hi>Strand;</hi> and came along with me, and told Mrs. <hi>Nicholls</hi> he would pay for my Lodging, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired her to let me have what I wanted; but before he went, gave me a particular charge, what ever I did to keep my ſelf private; but the next day going into the <hi>Strand,</hi> I met one Mr. <hi>Coop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> who had formerly been my Fathers Servant, who deſired me to go to drink with him, and told me he heard that I was ingaged in a buſineſs againſt my Father. I ſaid I had been with the King, and was counſelled by one <hi>Ely,</hi> and ſome others to draw up ſome Objections againſt the Plot; that <hi>Ely</hi> asked me what Perſons did write for my Father; and that I had mentioned his Name to <hi>Ely,</hi> and gave him in a liſt of ſeveral Perſons Names beſides, that did write for Doctor <hi>Oates,</hi> and that <hi>Ely</hi> was deſirous to ſpeak with him, and one Mr. <hi>Allen;</hi> and told me he would be at a Wine-Celler belonging to one <hi>Monſieur Choqueux</hi> a Chirurgeon in the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and if he could ſee ſuch a Perſon, he would willingly drink a Glaſs of Wine with him; and ſaid he was ſure of one Mr. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> formerly Doctor <hi>Oates</hi> his Clark, and one or two more whoſe Names I cannot remember; but ſaid, one of them would not declare any thing without a Protection; but they could ſwear ſuch things againſt <hi>Doctor Oates,</hi> that it would make a mans Hair ſtand an end to hear it; Mr. <hi>Coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> told me he would go with me to the Celler, where being very merry, and after ſeveral Healths, <hi>Ely</hi> askt him if his name was <hi>Cooper,</hi> and if he had not formerly been my Fathers Servant, and writ for him, who replied he had written ſeveral things for Doctor <hi>Tonge,</hi> but had nothing to ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Plot; ſays <hi>Ely,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cooper</hi> I do not deſire to compel you to any thing, but my thoughts are you might do very well to joyn with Mr. <hi>Tonge,</hi> and recollect your Memory, what Writings have gone through your Hands, and you ſhall have all poſſible Encouragement; and if you pleaſe I will furniſh you with a very good Lodging; and here is my very good Friend <hi>Monſieur Choqueux</hi> who I am confident will likewiſe aſſiſt you, to which Mr. <hi>Cooper</hi> made no reply, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed himſelf that he could ſtay no longer, having appointed other Buſineſs, and took his leave of them; no ſooner was he gone, but <hi>Ely</hi> replied, this <hi>Cooper Simſon</hi> is a cunning Shaver, I do not like him, but I hope you have not been ſo imprudent as to let him know where your Lodging is; I told him I had, and that I look't upon Mr. <hi>Cooper</hi> to be a very civil honeſt man. Then <hi>Ely</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to ſtorm, after his uſual rate, and ſaid, I had no more wit than a Gooſe; and it was to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for him to remove me from one Lodging to an other, if I would let all the World know where I was; and then Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> and <hi>Ely</hi> conſulted over a Glaſs of Wine, what they ſhould do with me; and <hi>Ely</hi> ſaid he thought it beſt to remove me to one of <hi>Choqueux</hi> Lodgings in the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> promiſed <hi>Ely</hi> he would provide me a Lodging, which accordingly he did; and that I ſhould want for nothing<hi>:</hi> and ſays <hi>Ely,</hi> ſince I perceive Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> is indiſpoſed, he ſhall ſay he is here only for the good of his health; yes ſays <hi>Choqueux</hi> that will do very well, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I being a Papiſt may be brought into Queſtion for entertaining him, and then they both parted, and <hi>Choqueux</hi> took me along with him.</p>
            <p>The next day <hi>Ely</hi> ſent for me to his Houſe, and after Dinner he told me he had received 10 <hi>l.</hi> by order from Mr. <hi>Chiffins,</hi> of which Sum he gave me 3 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> and bid me be a good husband with it, and at the ſame time ſent twenty Shillings to one Mrs. <hi>Fitzgerald</hi> to perſwade her to ſwear againſt my Father; and though he produced a Note under her Hand before the Councel, that he gave her that Money only out of Charity, ſhe being at that time very infirm, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this his plauſible pretence he was in hopes to have prevailed upon her, to have joyned with me, to ſwear againſt Doctor <hi>Oates;</hi> this was the greateſt Sum I ever had of <hi>Ely,</hi> which after I had received, he was ſtill importuning me to give him more Papers; and coming to my Lodging, he told me he had hired an excellent travelling Mare, and I muſt go with him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to <hi>Windſore;</hi> which I conſented to, and when we came within two Miles of <hi>Windſore,</hi> he told me, he muſt call at a place in the great Park, which belonged to Mr. <hi>May</hi> the keeper of the Privy-Purſe; and there we were both very kindly and civilly entertained by one Mr. <hi>Nun,</hi> Mr. <hi>Mays</hi> Gentleman, and after Dinner <hi>Ely</hi> told me he would ſeal up the Papers, I had given him, and would convey them to the King, and I expecting to go along with him, he ſaid I muſt not, but keep myſelf as private as I could, for ſhould I go to <hi>Windſore</hi> with him, he was afraid notice
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64123:5"/>
would be taken of me; he and Mr. <hi>Nun</hi> returned again in the Evening, and <hi>Ely</hi> told me he had carefully delivered that Paper to his Majeſty, and ſaid it was the materialleſt Paper I had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and told me he muſt go to <hi>London</hi> next morning, but ſtaid two or three Days longer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he muſt kiſs the Dukes Hand; then I came to Town with him again, and came to the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy,</hi> where Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> made me very welcome, and told me Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> if you hold on thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, he did not queſtion but he ſhould live to ſee me a great Man, and I might aſſure myſelf I ſhould want no Encouragement from him; for he would venture his Blood in the Cauſe, and for the good of the poor diſtreſſed Catholiques; who he ſaid were the moſt innocent though cruelly oppreſſed by the Proteſtants, that he was confident I believed it, and that he thought I was very real in what I went about, otherwiſe he would not have diſcourſed ſo much of his mind to me, and then we entred into other diſcourſe, and he ask't me what News there was at <hi>Windſor,</hi> I told him I had not been there, for <hi>Ely</hi> would not ſuffer me to go, and took my Leave of him, and went to my Lodging.</p>
            <p>Towards the latter end of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> or the beginning of <hi>September,</hi> I called at Mrs. <hi>Lanes</hi> Houſe, ſays ſhe Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> I thought you might have been more civil to me. I asked her what ſhe meant by that queſtion, for I never knew any thing of Incivility wherewith I could be taxed, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to herſelf and her Husband, but to my Power was willing to give them my Aſſiſtance; ſhe replied <hi>Ely</hi> had received 100 <hi>l.</hi> I told her if he had, 'twas more than I knew of, for he told me he received but 10 <hi>l.</hi> which he told me was very inconſiderable, expecting to have received a much bigger Sum, of which I received 3 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> Says ſhe, I took Captain <hi>Ely</hi> to be a very honeſt Man, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe you may aſſure your ſelf I would not have recommended him to you; but now I find he is a cheating Raſcal, yet ſays old <hi>Lane,</hi> I beat the Buſh and <hi>Ely</hi> caught the Bird; and ſaid, he promiſed him a Sum of Money, but it would be good when he could catch it, that he had been at his Lodging, but got no more of him than a Shilling; then ſhe called her Husband old Fool, becauſe he did not go himſelf to Mr. <hi>Chiffins;</hi> for ſhe believed having been one of the Yeomen of the Guard, his intereſt was as great at Court, as <hi>Elys;</hi> and told me, Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> if you will put your Buſineſs into my hands, I know a good Friend of mine who is acquainted with ſeveral great Perſons, that will procure you Money enough, but then you muſt leave <hi>Ely</hi> off, and come from your Lodging and lye at my Houſe, where you may be as private as you deſire; there being a back Dore by her Houſe, that went into the Privy Garden. I told her I would conſider on it, but ſaid, what between <hi>Ely</hi> and her, I was almoſt at my Wits end; and heartily wiſht I had never known, or been concern'd with either of them; ſays ſhe never be daunted, I'le warrant you, be but ruled by me, your Buſineſs will go very well, and told me I muſt go into <hi>Arundel</hi> Street, and inquire for Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> for ſhe was a Perſon ſhe went to viſit frequently, who had been very kind to her Son <hi>John Lane</hi> in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> and had promiſed her to give me what Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance ſhe could; I went as ſhe had directed me, and found out Mrs. <hi>Celliers</hi> Lodgings; ſhe told me ſhe did not know me, and askt me what was my Buſineſs; ſo I told her that I was recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to her by one Mrs. <hi>Lane,</hi> who told me ſhe was a Perſon that was very fit to aſſiſt me in my Concerns; ſhe replied Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> I am very glad to ſee you, I am very ſorry you have ſo little Encouragement in your Buſineſs, I muſt confeſs I have been bit already for my Zeal in promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Catholick Cauſe, and have expended ſeveral conſiderable Sums of Money upon that Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; but I have a Book to print which will ſufficiently vindicate my Innocency, from all the falſe and malicious Calumnys which are daily caſt upon me; and will publiſh to the World the grand Villanies and Rogueries of <hi>Oates,</hi> and <hi>Bedloe,</hi> and his Crue; and ſhall print nothing but what I have Witneſs to Confirm. Then ſhe ſaid ſhe would give me what Aſſiſtance ſhe could, and told me of a great man (but named him not) that would likewiſe joyn with her, but what ſhe did for me, muſt be very privately managed; and ſhe thought if I met her any where, the moſt convenient place would be to go over the Water, and there we might conſult together without any fear of Diſcovery; and told me when I came to her, it would be moſt convenient for me to come in the Evening, for fear of Diſcovery, for ſhe ſaid her Name was already brought upon the Stage of the World, and therefore though ſhe was willing to aſſiſt me privately, yet ſhe would not be ſeen to appear in countenancing my Buſineſs, but if I had any thing to deliver to her, ſhe would carefully convey away any Papers to the Kings or Dukes Hands. I told her I had no Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and then ſhe appointed me to come and ſee her the next Day in the Evening, I came again to her Houſe, but ſhe not being within, according to her deſire I left a Note with her Maid, I had been there to wait upon her; and went away to find out <hi>Ely</hi> in <hi>Holborne,</hi> who gave me more Encouragement than ſhe did, and never went to her again.</p>
            <p>Some few Days after Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> invited one <hi>Crawly, Ely,</hi> myſelf and one Mr. <hi>Hays</hi> with ſome others to a Fiſh Dinner, in the <hi>Savoy;</hi> where amongſt other general Diſcourſe, <hi>Choqueux</hi> told me that he would gladly have me acquainted with <hi>Crawly,</hi> that he was a very honeſt man,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64123:5"/>
and a well-wiſner to my Buſineſs; and that he had informed him that ſome time ſince he got ſome Papers to be delivered in to the Duke againſt my Father; to which <hi>Crawly</hi> replied he had given in ſome Papers againſt him by one Mr. <hi>Sherridon,</hi> and ſhould be very glad to renew that little Acquaintance he had formerly injoyed, when he writ for my Father, and that he was very glad to hear that I was imbarqued in the ſame Cauſe with him; that he had heard ſome whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings about the Town concerning my Buſineſs, and was very joyful that he had the Opportunity of diſcourſing me concerning that Affair; and ſaid he would give me a more large Account of his Buſineſs, and would take a more ſeaſonable time to inform me of it, but aſſured me that mine had a very near Relation to his, and appointed me to meet him the next day at his Lodging, which then was at one Mrs. <hi>Yates</hi> Houſe in <hi>Monmouth</hi> Street near St. <hi>Giles</hi> in the Fields: and I promiſed him I would not fail to be with him in the Evening, for I was very deſirous to hear his Buſineſs, with ſuch like Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>The next Day I went to find out Mr. <hi>Crawly,</hi> and there he gave me an Account of his Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which was to my beſt Remembrance to this Effect, that about two years ſince, (which he ſaid he remembred very well becauſe of the general Colds that were then in Town,) he had ſome Writings of my Fathers to Tranſcribe concerning Parliaments, and a Copy of Doctor <hi>Oates</hi> his Depoſitions, to Tranſcribe fairly; that Sr. <hi>William Waller</hi> coming there about to ſearch for Prieſts, had notice of him, who was then very bad with a Cold; that Sr. <hi>William Waller</hi> asked him what Employment he followed, he ſaid he ſtudied the Law, and took down ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers which lay on the Shelf, and looking on them ſaid theſe Papers are Doctor <hi>Tonges</hi> hand, and he knew it very well; to which <hi>Crawly</hi> replyed they were his Hand-Writing, and were ſome Overtures of his about Parliaments, and he imployed him to write them out fair; that Sr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Waller</hi> took thoſe Papers away from him, and bid the ſaid <hi>Crawly</hi> go along with him, but upon his the ſaid <hi>Crawlys</hi> Requeſt, telling Sr. <hi>William Waller</hi> he was very much indiſpoſed by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Cold; Sr. <hi>William</hi> ſuffered him to return to his Lodging, upon Promiſe that he would come to his Houſe the next Day.</p>
            <p>Moreover he told me that he went to Sr. <hi>William Wallers</hi> Houſe, where he ſaid Sr. <hi>William Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> was at Dinner, and my Father with him, that Sr. <hi>William</hi> ſaid to my Father, Doctor <hi>Tonge</hi> I took ſome Papers away from this Gentleman laſt Night, which he ſaid were your Hand, and was deſirous to know whether you knew him; to which he told me my Father made Anſwer; That he never ſaw him before in his Life, and did not know that he ever gave any ſuch Papers unto him; that then he ſaid he took his Leave; and I asking him whether Sr. <hi>William</hi> did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore thoſe Papers again to my Father; he ſaid he was not certain whether he did or not; but had he had them in his Poſſeſſion, his intent was to have given them in with his other Papers to the Duke; for he lookt upon them to be very dangerous and treaſonable Papers; that he was very deſirous to ſpeak with Sr. <hi>William Waller</hi> concerning it, but could never ſince have the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to ſpeak with him: this <hi>Crawly</hi> I ſuppoſe is a Papiſt, and is an Iriſh man, and would gladly have perſwaded me to leave <hi>Ely,</hi> and would have undertaken to manage his own, and my Buſineſs himſelf; for he ſaid he had ſtudied the Law ſome conſiderable time, and therefore could give me better Advice than <hi>Ely;</hi> who as he was informed (though he might be very Zealous for the good of the Catholiques) was wholly ignorant in the Law; he bid me conſider of it, if I would put my Buſineſs into his Hands, <hi>I</hi> told him I would conſider on it, and ſo took my leave of him.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Cooper</hi> had now found out my Lodgings in the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and came often to ſee me, and I told him that Mr. <hi>Choqueux,</hi> and <hi>Ely</hi> were very importunate to have Mrs. <hi>Fitzgerald</hi> removed from her own Lodging, into one of <hi>Choqueux</hi> beſt Rooms, which he ſaid was very well hung, and fit to entertain her, and told me if ſhe would come thither ſhe ſhould want for no manner of Conveniency, and have all things to her Content and Satisfaction; and propoſed to have her brought in a Sedan, if ſhe could not come by Water; Mr. <hi>Cooper</hi> ſaid ſhe was ſo very infirm that it was altogether impoſſible ſhe could be removed as yet, without being very prejudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to her Health; and then entring into Diſcourſe with me about my own Buſineſs, I told him I could not tell what <hi>Choqueux</hi> and <hi>Ely</hi> intended to do with me<hi>:</hi> but here they kept me confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to a Chamber, that I ſaw none but them, and that I was extraordinary weary of that Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Confinement<hi>:</hi> and deſiring him to ſtay a little, I went to call Mr. <hi>Choqueux:</hi> and when I returned again Mr. <hi>Cooper</hi> was gone, and took away two of my Papers, which were brought to the Councel, one of which was read to me, but the other Doctor <hi>Oates</hi> told my Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, he could not find: the next Day I miſt my Papers, and <hi>Ely</hi> coming to ſee me I told him ſomebody had taken ſome Papers from me, and I could not imagine who it ſhould be: then ſays he that Raſcal <hi>Cooper</hi> has betray'd us<hi>:</hi> I gave you ſufficient Warning of him, ſo did Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> likewiſe more than once, but you would not take our Advice: therefore
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64123:6"/>
you muſt remove immediately out of this Room; but not well knowing whither, he went to his Friend <hi>Monſieur Choqueux</hi> to conſult with him about it; and they preſently hurried me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in great haſt to one Mr. <hi>Salsburys</hi> near the Glaſſ-houſe in the <hi>Savoy;</hi> where Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> bargained with Mrs. <hi>Salisbury</hi> to pay three Shillings a Week for my Lodging, and for my Dyet, until he could provide for me to Dine ſomewhere elſe; and <hi>Choqueux</hi> and <hi>Ely</hi> did both lay a very ſtrict Charge on me, to keep my ſelf very private, and never to have any more Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with Mr. <hi>Cooper,</hi> for he would certainly ruine the whole Deſign; and if I ſtirred out he would certainly find me, for he was often ſeen in the <hi>Savoy:</hi> I had not been above a Week at Mrs. <hi>Salisburys,</hi> but <hi>Ely</hi> comes to me again: and I ask't him what News there was abroad, for I lived a kind of <hi>Anchorets</hi> Life, and ſaw no body, and ſhould be extreme Melancholly were it not for the Society I took in ſome pleaſant Books which Mr. <hi>Salisbury</hi> lent me: he ſaid there was no good News, for he was informed that Doctor <hi>Oates</hi> had delivered a Petition in to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel againſt me and himſelf, for Subornation and Perjury, and Defaming the Kings Evidence; but bid me be of good Courage, for all his Huffing and Bluſtring could do me no harm, for he was told he found ſuch cold Entertainment, that he believed he would not appear againſt me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in haſt<hi>:</hi> that Doctor <hi>Oates</hi> was heard to ſay, to a Perſon of Honour theſe Words, Now my Lord if you do not ſtand by me, I and the Kingdome's ruin'd: and ſaid becauſe thoſe Papers were all looſe, and apt to be ſcattered and loſt, which I delivered to his Majeſty, he thought it would be very convenient for me to recollect my Memory, and draw all thoſe Papers into one ſheet of Paper; that being informed that my Father was very well acquainted with ſeveral Lords which were thought to be rigid Presbyterians; he bid me be ſure to remember to inſert ſome of their Names, as Contrivers of the popiſh Plot; for he ſaid that ſeveral Perſons about the Town did believe it to be a Presbyterian Plot, and the Papiſts had no hands in it, and that he had one of my Papers and would ſend it me; I told him I would endeavour to draw up thoſe Papers into one Sheet, but I had no Coppies by me, which would very much help me, if I had kept any; he ſaid Mr. <hi>Crawly</hi> had drawn up his Papers again at large, that there was at leaſt two or three Sheets of Paper, which he was ready to depoſe upon Oath, and did intend when mine were written out, to deliver them together; that Mr. <hi>Crawly</hi> was a very zealous Perſon in my Buſineſs, and that I might help to corroborate his Teſtimony, which would make his Evidence the more conſiderable, the more Witneſſes were in it, and did joyn themſelves together to defend and make out the ſame thing; and deſired me to diſpatch my Paper as ſoon as I could; but not being very well, I did not then do it, and ſent him a Letter which to my beſt remembrance was to this Effect, for I have not the Coppy by me; That my Sentiment was I ſhould be look't upon as a great Raſcal, and a very undutiful Perſon for what I had already done; that I was at preſent very much indiſpoſed and could not Write. To which he returned me this ſhort Anſwer, a foul Coppy of one of the Papers he delivered to the King, being incloſed in the Letter, the Words of which were to this Effect.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I <hi>Have here incloſed ſent your Paper, pray uſe your Care and Diligence to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedite the Matter</hi> (which dubious Words needing ſome Expoſition being ſo cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly worded, It was to Tranſcribe all thoſe looſe Papers into one Sheet of Paper) <hi>againſt Wedneſday Morning, and in the Interim be Merry.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>I am yours faithfully</hi> S. Ely.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>On the Thurſday Morning very early comes <hi>Ely</hi> to me, and having written out that Paper, he took it along with him; and told me that Mr. <hi>Crawly,</hi> and one Mr. <hi>Murphy</hi> an Iriſh-man, and a Schoolmaſter about the Town, and who had formerly been a Student at <hi>Paris</hi> for ſome time, would likewiſe go along with us to <hi>Windſore,</hi> and taking a Sculler we landed as near to <hi>Chearing-Croſs</hi> as we could, and the Coach not being ready, we went and ſtayed at a Strong-water Shop near the <hi>Goat</hi> Tavern; where <hi>Ely</hi> changed a Guinny, and there we all three took Coach, and went for <hi>Windſore,</hi> and ſome Strangers being with us, <hi>Ely</hi> whiſpered me in the Ear, and ſaid I was generally too talkative, and bid me have a great care I did not ſpeak a word of any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64123:6"/>
we were going about, whilſt we were in the Coach; when we came to <hi>Windſor, Ely</hi> gave us a Treat at the French Ordinary, and after Dinner inquiring for a Lodging for us, we were directed to a Pewterers Houſe near the <hi>Garter</hi> Tavern, where <hi>Ely</hi> bargained for our Lodging; and the next Day <hi>Ely</hi> took mine and <hi>Crawly's</hi> Papers, and carried them to the King or the Duke; and told me that his Majeſty ſaid that my Uncle had been with one of the Secretaries of State, and that I had given my Uncle a Recantation, and declared in that Paper, that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts had ſet me on to ſwear againſt my Father, and Doctor <hi>Oates,</hi> that they were the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the Popiſh Plot; and <hi>Ely</hi> ſaid he told the King, that he was ſo far from believing any ſuch thing, that on the contrary he was ſo confident of my Reallity; that if it were ſo he would give his Majeſties Tooth-drawer leave to pull out all his Teeth one after another; and when he returned again, he ſaid though it were not true, I ſhould do very well to vindicate my ſelf to the King from that Calumny and Aſperſion (as he termed it) that my Uncle had caſt upon me, ſo he and <hi>Crawly</hi> drew up ſome Words to that purpoſe, and carried them to the King; which Words were That I never had given my Uncle any Recantation: After the Papers were delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Crawly</hi> went ſeveral times to the Caſtle to look out Mr. <hi>Sherridon,</hi> who as he ſaid was a great Favourite of the Dukes, and one in whom he did very much conſide; but could not as yet find him out, though he was informed he was certainly in Town, and ſaid he would very gladly have ſpoken with Mr. <hi>Sherridon,</hi> becauſe he faithfully had promiſed him upon the firſt delivery of his Papers into his Hands, (which was ſome conſiderable time before he heard any thing of my bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs) that he would ſafely deliver his Papers to the Dukes Hands; but could never ſince the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery of them, hear any thing concerning it; and ſeemed to be very much troubled. <hi>Ely</hi> bid him not trouble his Head with Mr. <hi>Sherridon,</hi> for he told <hi>Crawly</hi> he believed he was much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken in him, that he was not ſo real in his Buſineſs as he took him to be; and that the next Day he would give him an account of his Papers from the Duke himſelf; and getting up very early in the Morning, he told <hi>Crawly</hi> at his return from the Caſtle, he had been with the Duke, and kiſt his Hand, and askt him concerning thoſe Papers which were given to Mr. <hi>Sherridon,</hi> but that his Royal Highneſs anſwered he did not remember that he had received any ſuch Papers; and <hi>Ely</hi> ſaid as ſoon as he came in, all the reſt withdrew to the other ſide of the Room; and ſaid he had above half an Hours Diſcourſe with the Duke, but did not mention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Particulars, excepting <hi>Crawlys</hi> Papers, which Papers <hi>Crawly</hi> pretended were tranſcribed out of my Fathers Originals concerning Parliaments; and the two <hi>Murphys</hi> both Papiſts were to be Witneſſes to thoſe Papers; and one Mr. <hi>Bryan,</hi> now or very lately a Priſoner in the <hi>Gatehouſe,</hi> concerning the Duke of <hi>Buckingham;</hi> was likewiſe to be an Evidence, from whom (he told me) he had thoſe Papers of my Fathers, becauſe <hi>(Crawly</hi> ſaid) being written very badly, <hi>Brian</hi> could not read them very well, therefore deſired him to tranſcribe them. <hi>Ely</hi> whilſt he was at <hi>Windſor,</hi> went often to ſpeak with Mr. <hi>Chiffins,</hi> but he little regarded him, and ſaid he made him wait ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times an hour or two, before he could get admiſſion to ſpeak with him; ſo that wanting Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney he was compel'd to pawn his Silver hilted Sword, to one of the Drawers of the <hi>Garter</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern for 20 <hi>s.</hi> and ſeveral other things, his Ring from his Finger, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to ſupply us with Money for Dyet, beſides what he borrowed of the Gentle-woman where we uſually dined; and ſaid he would Pawn his Shirt from his Back, where he ſaw Perſons ſo real as we were, in ſuch an impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Concern as we were about; but finding <hi>VVindſor</hi> very chargeable, and his Money near gon, he ſent a Letter to his Friend <hi>Mounſieur Choqueux</hi> to deſire him to ſend him three Pound, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he could not get from <hi>VVindſor,</hi> for he and his Company were pawned for it; and could not pay for his Lodging before he received it; <hi>Choqueux</hi> ſent him three Pounds, and told me he was troubled to get it, being forced to pawn a piece of Plate; then <hi>Murphy</hi> ſeeing I ſuppoſe that <hi>Ely</hi> was only put off with Delays, and that there was no probability of his doing any good at <hi>VVindſor,</hi> having ſome Money left, begged <hi>Elys</hi> Excuſe, and went to <hi>London,</hi> becauſe his Schollers expected his coming, and wiſht him all imaginable Succeſs in his Buſineſs; and promiſed him that his Aſſiſtance ſhould not be wanting, in the furthering of the Buſineſs; and that when it came to the Touch-ſtone he ſhould find it ſo. After <hi>Crawly</hi> and I had ſtaid thirteen or fourteen Days, <hi>Ely</hi> hired a pair of Oars for us, and gave me a Crown to bear our Charges to <hi>London,</hi> and landing at the <hi>Savoy</hi> Stairs I came to Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> Lodgings; and told him what had paſt ſince our being at <hi>VVindſor,</hi> and <hi>Choqueux</hi> ſaid he very much wondered we ſtaid ſo long; for he did expect us within two or three Days; and had provided a gentile Dinner for us, and ſeveral Bottles of Wine, to entertain us; I told him the Buſineſs went but very croſly at <hi>VVindſor,</hi> that <hi>Ely</hi> did nothing but ſtorm and fret ſince he came thither, becauſe he found himſelf ſo ſlighted, and met with ſuch perpetual Diſappointments; that he had ſent a huffing Letter to Mr. <hi>Chiffins</hi> to his Country Houſe called <hi>Filburds</hi> near <hi>VVindſor</hi> by Mr. <hi>Murphy,</hi> but Mr. <hi>Chiffins</hi> was gone ere he came, and that he thought Mr. <hi>Chiffins</hi> did very little regard him, that he told me he would be at <hi>Lond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:64123:7"/>
the next Day; but did not come till the Court removed from <hi>Windſor</hi> to <hi>Whitchal,</hi> by reaſon he was very much indiſpoſed by a Surffet with drinking too much Clarret Wine, and a great Looſneſs which was ſo violent upon him, that he could ſcarce ſit his Horſe, which was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that he ſtaid longer than he intended to do.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Elys</hi> return to <hi>London,</hi> he came to Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> Lodgings, and told me he believed my Papers were ſufficient to overthrow the Evidence, but would I do the Buſineſs thoroughly, and ſtrike at the Root of the Plot; it muſt be by drawing up ſome Papers relating to the Death of Sr. <hi>Edmund-bury Godfrey,</hi> for he ſaid none ſhould make him believe, that thoſe Papiſts which were generally believed to Murder him, had any Hand in his Blood, for he ſaid it was much more probable that the Proteſtants did it, that they might be revenged upon the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques; and likewiſe added that there was a Club of Presbyterian Lords in the City, who plotted the Deſtruction of the eſtabliſht Monarchical Government; that the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> went often thither, and they made uſe of him only to promote their own Ambitious Deſigns; never intending (whatever might be their Pretenſions) to make him King of <hi>England,</hi> but they only gave him fair Words to maintain and countenance their Faction, and therefore his Health was to the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and God dam all the Fanaticks; he ſaid likewiſe that Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> was a great Raſcal, that he knew nothing of Sr. <hi>E. B. G.</hi> Death, but what was extorted from him by ſeveral Lords that came to ſee him; and ſays he was ready, and ſeveral others that were then in <hi>Newgate</hi> with him, to depoſe upon Oath, that he cry'd and rav'd a long time like a mad Man, when he was viſited by ſeveral Perſons of Quality, and deſired to confeſs the truth of that barbarous and bloody Murther; that all they could get of him, was he knew nothing, he knew nothing, he would not be guilty of innocent Blood, no Guilt, no Guilt oh King; and ſuch ſtrange Expreſſions, till through the important Sollicitations of thoſe that came to ſee him, he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed on to ſave his own Life, to confeſs that which according to his own Confeſſion he knew nothing of; which is much the ſame Story that the Lady <hi>Rampant,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> the Popiſh Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife, relates in her lying Popiſh Legend concerning Mr. <hi>Praunce;</hi> likewiſe he ſaid that the right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> was the chief of that rebellious Fanatical Club; and told me a Story concerning a very dangerous and treaſonable Paper, which was ſuppoſed to be written by a Perſon who was kept a long time a Priſoner in the <hi>Tower,</hi> becauſe he had thoughts to make Diſcovery of the Popiſh Plot, that there was a great Sum of Money offered for any Perſon that could take him; for the Paper was fathered on him; but by the contents of it, it ſeemed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh of Fanatick Principles, and that my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> was by ſome ſuſpected to be the Author of it; likewiſe he ſays that it was by the Lord <hi>Shaftsburys</hi> Orders and Directions that the reſt moved, he being accounted by all Perſons, an excellent Statesman, and very profound Politician; and ſaid moreover that he was informed that the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> was come in, and made ſome very great Diſcovery to his Majeſty concerning the Deſigns of the Presbyterians againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which if it was ſo he ſaid, then adieu to the Popiſh Plot, for if this be true, (which I do not much doubt, having received it from ſuch very good Hands,) this will help admirable well to back what you have written concerning ſome Lords, thought to be well wiſhers to the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Party; upon ſeveral Diſcourſes which we have had together upon that Subject; upon this Queſtion of theſe Lords I was examined before his Majeſty, and my Lord Chancellour; that what I writ concerning them was upon the Inſtigation of <hi>Ely,</hi> who ſaid if there were any Plot, it muſt be a Presbyterian one, for his part he ſaid, he thought I ſhould do the Nation a very great piece of Service, by undeciving of them as to that particular of Sr. <hi>E. B. G.</hi> Death, by diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what I knew of it. I told him I was ſo far from knowing any thing of his Death, that I was then out of Town, when the firſt Diſcourſe of his Death was ſpread abroad; I told him there was ſufficient Circumſtances, and manifeſt Evidence to prove that the Papiſts were the Authors of that bloody Act; I told him I knew one Mr. <hi>VVren</hi> who was a Gentleman that I had ſeen ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times with my Father, but had no acquaintance with him; that I thought did make ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Diſcovery to my Father concerning his Death, after Mr. <hi>Bedloe</hi> had declared his; but came in too late, and had no encouragement to make any farther Enquiry, and <hi>Ely</hi> asking where that Perſon Lodged, I told him I could not tell, having not ſeen him for ſome time: he asked me if I could no ways find out his Lodging, I told him I believed Mr <hi>Cooper</hi> might direct me, and he deſired me when I ſaw Mr. <hi>Cooper</hi> that I would enquire of him where his Lodging was, and I promiſed him I would, and ſo took my Leave of him.</p>
            <p>The next morning I went to Mr. <hi>Coopers</hi> Lodging, and askt him if he knew where Mr. <hi>VVrens</hi> Lodging was, for <hi>Ely</hi> had a great deſire to ſpeak with him; he ſaid he believed he could, with a little recollection of his Memory, for he ſaid when he lived with my Father, he had been once or twice at his Lodging; then he ſaid if he were not miſtaken, he lodged in <hi>Dukes</hi> Street in <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent</hi> Garden, and having found out his Lodging, a Maid came to us, and ſaid that Mr. <hi>VVren</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:64123:7"/>
was gone to the Tower, and they did not expect him that Day, ſo we both returned to <hi>Ely,</hi> and told him we had found out Mr. <hi>Wrens</hi> Lodgings; then he askt me if I had ever ſeen what his Diſcovery was; I told him I had never read it, then <hi>Ely</hi> replied if you never ſaw it, it is probable Mr. <hi>Wrens</hi> diſcovery agrees with <hi>Bedloes,</hi> and <hi>Praunces</hi> Narrative, and that will do us no good, ſo that without I were certain what it was he could ſay, I would have nothing to do with him; ſo that Deſign was quite broke off, <hi>Ely</hi> being I ſuppoſe fearful of Mr. <hi>Wren,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Mr. <hi>Cooper</hi> nor my ſelf, never went to look after him any more,</p>
            <p>In the Evening Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> came to ſee me, and told me he knew a very ingenious and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Perſon, one Mr. <hi>L'eſtrange,</hi> whom he would gladly have me acquainted with, for he was late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made a Juſtice of the Peace, and was very ſorry he did not think of him before; for being often abroad about his Occaſions, he could not keep me company, nor aſſiſt me ſo much as he deſired; (and ſaid) he was very much obliged to <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> for mentioning his Name, in his Witty Narrative, (which he calls <hi>L'eſtranges</hi> Narrative of the Plot) for clearing and vindicating him from that lying Story of the Firebal which he kept by him, in his Chamber, reported that they were for the fyring of the City, about which he ſaid there was ſuch a Noiſe, that ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Files of Souldiers were ſent from the Councel to guard all that long Paſſage in the <hi>Savoy,</hi> from the Gate to his own Door, and were ordered to ſuffer none to go in and out; he then ask'd me if I knew <hi>L'eſtrange,</hi> I reply'd I did not, but have heard ſeveral mention his Name; and told him if I were not miſtaken he licenced Books. He told me it was the very ſame Perſon, and he would if I pleaſed introduce me into his Acquaintance; I told him Mr. <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> had the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute about the Town of a witty Man, but I never ſaw him in my life; ſays <hi>Choqueux</hi> he was with me laſt Night, but did not ſtay long, but is excellent good Company, and of whoſe Society I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was extreme deſirous; I have invited him to morrow about ſeven or eight in the Evening to a Collation, and then you may diſcourſe him.</p>
            <p>According as <hi>Choqueux</hi> had told me, he brought <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> with him, and there was none in the Room but my ſelf, before their coming in, though he ſpeaks of two young Men in his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alogue, but Lyes are accounted ſmall Faults with him, he can eaſily ſwallow them, and he might be pardoned for ſuch Crimes, did he not err very groſly in very material Circumſtances; as ſoon as Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> came in he told <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> that my Name was <hi>Tonge,</hi> then <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> ſaid Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> have I not ſeen you formerly at your Fathers Lodgings at <hi>Whitehal.</hi> I told him that to my Remembrance I never ſaw him there, but that I heard my Father mention his Name more than once, upon the Account of a Book which he wrote called the <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> which he ſtopped and would not permit it to be Licenced; and that if I were not very miſtaken (and therefore I would not be too confident in what I ſaid) my Father informed me that he had put out ſeveral things in that Book, and ſaid it was a very dangerous Piece, and unleſs he would permit him to model it according to his own Capricious Humour, he could not Licence it, and thereupon my Father was much troubled at his Sawcineſs, and ſent for his Book again; theſe Words in <hi>L'eſtranges</hi> Dialogue, <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> makes <hi>Choqueux</hi> to ſpeak, for theſe are his own Words, yes (ſays Mr. <hi>Choqueux)</hi> for refuſing to Licence his <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> which he took very ill at your Hands, of which Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> knew nothing of, but I ſhall take no farther no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of <hi>L'eſtranges</hi> Abuſive and Lying Dialogue, for the whole Book is altogether extravagant and incoherent; and therefore not worth my while to make more Quotations out of it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall proceed, then Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> Recommended me to <hi>L'eſtrange,</hi> as a Perſon very wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of my Acquaintance, and told him I had drawn up ſeveral Papers as Objections againſt the Plot; and he did preſume I ſhould be very glad of his Aſſiſtance therein; <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> told me he would to his Power Aſſiſt me in what he could, and ask'd me where my Papers were, for he would gladly peruſe them; for he was informed thoſe Papers had very material Things in them againſt the Plot; that he was a great admirer of all ſuch things, as he did not queſtion he had demonſtrated to the World, by his Collections he had made concerning the Popiſh Plot, where Doctor <hi>Oates,</hi> was pleaſed to be ſilent; and ſaid that for his Part, he found the whole Plot was repleniſhed with nothing elſe but Improbabilities, and ridiculous Abſurdities; and inſtanced in ſeveral general Tranſactions of the Plot, to wit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the unlikelihood of ſhooting his Majeſty with ſilver Bullets in a ſcrew'd Gun, and <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> ſaid he would prove it by Reaſon, that if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one ſhoot off ſuch a Gun charged with ſilver Bullets, the ſilver Bullet would not give way, but come out a Slug; and another ridiculous Story he mentioned, that if Doctor <hi>Oates</hi> went over to St. <hi>Omers,</hi> and diſcovered the Popiſh Plot, by being there converſant with the Prieſts and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, he ſaid it was very ſtrange he could not tell, when he came over for <hi>England,</hi> where he firſt Landed; and then <hi>Choqueux</hi> and <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> fell into other Diſcourſe concerning the late Wars; and <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> told him he did intend to write Prince <hi>Ruperts</hi> Life, and askt <hi>Choqueux</hi> whether he could give him any Aſſiſtance; he ſaid he had ſome Memorials relating to the late
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64123:8"/>
Wars, but they were at <hi>Paris,</hi> ſo they both parted, and going out with <hi>L'eſtrange,</hi> I asked him when I ſhould wait upon him, and if he had any Writing, I would tranſcribe any thing for him which he had to Print, but he ſaid he had no ſuch Buſineſs, but that any Evening he ſhould be glad to ſee me, and Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> at his Houſe in <hi>Holborne,</hi> and went his way from us.</p>
            <p>The next Day after Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> went to <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> his Houſe, and told me he was newly gone out; but he ſaid to morrow in the Evening I ſhould go along with him to <hi>L'eſtrange,</hi> and <hi>Crawly</hi> coming to the <hi>Savoy</hi> before we were gon, went along with us; whom I ſuppoſe <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> had no Acquaintance with; but <hi>Crawly</hi> went thinking he might have ſomething to ſay to him in relation to his Papers; ſo ſoon as we came into the Room, where <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> was, he deſired Mr. <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queux</hi> and <hi>Crawly</hi> to withdraw, for he ſaid it look'd too much like a Conſultation, who went out and expected my coming out in the Street; then being together, he asked me whether I had a Coppy of that Information which was delivered to the King; I told him I had not, only ſome looſe Papers relating to it; but I could recite ſeveral material Paſſages of it; then <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> writ them down; and askt me whether I had no more to ſay, I told him I had not; and ſaid when he had more Leaſure, and had all my Informations he would ſwear me to them; I told him I did not care to be ſworn to any of my Papers, for when <hi>Ely</hi> had often deſired me I always refuſed it, for I was ſufficiently Conſcious of the great Undutifulneſs, and what an imparalelled degree of Impiety it would be, if I ſhould ſwear againſt my Father, to take away his Life; then <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> ſaid he did not deſire to compel me to any thing, but now he was very buſy, and had much Writing to diſpatch, and deſired me to call on him ſome other time; ſo I took my Leave of him, and he gave me as I was going, one or two of his Pamphlets, and went to find out Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> and <hi>Crawly</hi> who expected my coming out, but being both gon away I went to <hi>Elys</hi> Houſe, and there I found them both, and <hi>Choqueux</hi> asked me what Mr. <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> ſaid to me, and how he reſented my Buſineſs. I told him I thought he approved of it very well, but ſaid he was very buſy, and took ſome Notes of what I ſaid in Writing, and deſired me to come ſome other time; and Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> ſaid it was very well, and that things of that Nature muſt not be puſht on too faſt, but be managed with mature Deliberation; and ſaid ere it was long I ſhould wait on <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> again; then <hi>Crawly</hi> replied he was the likelieſt Perſon that <hi>Choqueux</hi> could have pitcht on to do my Buſineſs; being a Perſon whoſe Parts and Ingenuity he much admired; and <hi>Crawly</hi> went to his Lodging in <hi>Monmouth</hi> Street, and I went with <hi>Choqueux</hi> to the <hi>Savoy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About a week after or thereabouts, there was a Meeting appointed by <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> and <hi>Ely</hi> at a Tavern near <hi>Chearing-croſs,</hi> where were in the lower Room <hi>Choqueux, Crawly,</hi> the two <hi>Murphys</hi> and my ſelf, and <hi>Ely</hi> and <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> were above Stairs, before any of the reſt came; where after we had drunk ſeveral Bottles of Wine, <hi>Ely</hi> came down and ſaid that Letter which was very long, was to be fairly Tranſcribed that Night, and ſent to the King; <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> ſlipt down Stairs, and never came into the Room to us, though I was told, he did aſſiſt <hi>Ely</hi> to Indite it, and was with him above Stairs; then we all parted to our ſeveral Lodgings, and I went with <hi>Choqueux</hi> to the <hi>Savoy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not long after this, I was informed by Mr. <hi>Choqueux,</hi> that there had been one of the Kings Meſſengers, with a Warrant for him, and his Friend <hi>Ely,</hi> to appear before the Councel; at which <hi>Choqueux</hi> ſeemed to be very much ſtartled, and ſaid he had been no ways concerned with me on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in relation to my Health; and he did not queſtion but I would vindicate him before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel; I told him I could not ſurmiſe before hand what Queſtions would be asked me by the Lords of the Councel, but he might aſſure himſelf I would ſpeak nothing but the Truth, let it light where it would; and in the Morning <hi>Ely,</hi> and <hi>Choqueux,</hi> with Doctor <hi>Oates</hi> were before the Councel, where was expected I ſhould have been, but did not come<hi>:</hi> but the next Week after I was likewiſe ſummoned to appear with them; and the Day before I went I informed <hi>Ely</hi> and <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queux</hi> that I had a Note in my Trunck, which I had from Doctor <hi>Caſtle</hi> a little before I left him, that was at Mr. <hi>Kings</hi> in <hi>Shandoys</hi> Street, which I thought might do me a kindneſs, and <hi>Ely,</hi> and <hi>Choqueux</hi> told me it would be very neceſſary that I ſhould have it; <hi>Ely</hi> came the next Morning in a Hackney Coach to the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and ſhook me by the Hand, Now Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> ſays he, you are this Day to go before the Councel; and do not fear but your Buſineſs is done, carry your ſelf but couragiouſly this firſt Brunt, and you ſhall have Backers enough to aſſiſt you; I wiſh you good Succeſs, and ſaid he would meet me at the Councel, at the appointed Hour between nine and ten of the Clock, but I am afraid you have not Courage enough to go manfully through with it; and I wiſh I were in your Caſe, to anſwer for you before the Councel, in a Buſineſs of ſuch general good, and great Importance to the Nation; you will never have the like Opportunity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to prefer your ſelf as is now in your Hands; therefore be ſure you recollect your ſelf very well before you go, otherwiſe you will be trapt in your Diſcourſe, and you may be ſure Doctor <hi>Oates</hi> will thunder againſt you ſufficiently, who is exceedingly inraged againſt you, by what I
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64123:8"/>
ſaw when Mr. <hi>Choqueux,</hi> and my ſelf, were laſt before the Councel; when <hi>Ely</hi> was gone <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queux</hi> gave me a Guinny to fetch that Paper, and a Gentleman an Acquaintance of <hi>Choqueux</hi> went along with me in a Hackney Coach to Mr. <hi>Kings</hi> to fetch that Paper; and thence he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried me to <hi>Whitehal,</hi> and coming before the Councel, having been askt ſeveral Queſtions by their Lordſhips in relation to the Plot, and three or four times Examined by my Lord Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour; I was committed to <hi>Newgate</hi> for high Miſdemeanours, and indeavouring by falſe Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Subornation of Perjury to defame the Kings Evidence, and all the proſecutions of the Popiſh Plot; I was firſt brought by one of the Kings Meſſengers into the Preſs-Yard, and there one <hi>Gyles</hi> that ſtood in the Pillory, inſinuated himſelf into my Acquaintance; and told me I muſt not be Melancholly, nor caſt down, for many times the Innocent had the misfortune to Suffer, but ſaid my Buſineſs was never the worſe, though I was committed to <hi>Newgate;</hi> and told me if I would not be wavering, but firm and Reſolute, he did not much queſtion but he could ingage Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> that ſhe ſhould ſtand my Friend, and procure me Money, and what elſe I ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of her; whilſt I was in the Preſs-yeard one Mrs. <hi>Elmes</hi> came likewiſe to me, and told me that now all the Eyes of the Catholicks were upon me; and requeſted me what ever I did not to go back, but ſtrenuouſly maintain my firſt Papers; and ſaid ſhe had a conſiderable Eſtate, and I ſhould never want, whilſt ſhe had a Farthing in the World, and by her Intereſt ſhe ſaid ſhe could procure more Friends, which would relieve me if they ſaw me couragious for the Catholique In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, to which I ſeemingly reply'd I would, ſo ſhe took her leave; this Woman is a very zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Papiſt, and an intimate Acquaintance of <hi>Monſieur Choqueux.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilſt I was in the Preſs-yard, being adviſ'd by one of Mr. <hi>Choqueux</hi> Acquaintance, to write to <hi>Ely</hi> for ſome Relief, during my Confinement, and to deſire him to bail me out of Priſon, I did, as I had been informed his Friend <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> was Bail for him, and after ſome expectation I received this Letter from <hi>Ely,</hi> very cunningly and cautiouſly Penned, but the whole drift of it, (as any Perſon may eaſily perceive) was to draw me into a Snare, to write <hi>Choqueux</hi> ſuch a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that what he had done for me, was only for the good of my Health; and that he was no ways concerned in the Subornation to induce me to ſwear againſt my Father and Doctor <hi>Oates,</hi> that they were the contrivers of the Popiſh Plot; Mr. <hi>Chiffins</hi> ſent <hi>Ely</hi> a Letter that Mr <hi>Choque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ux</hi> ſhould take care of me in regard of my Health; and <hi>Ely</hi> ſhow'd me the Letter, nevertheleſs <hi>Choqueux</hi> was continually prompting me on, and was extreme zealous for the Catholick Intereſt, and ſaid he was very glad to hear of my forwardneſs to vindicate them; and thought I was the only Perſon in England that might be a means to make the Catholique Religion Flouriſh in theſe Kingdoms; and ſaid he cared not what he beſtowed to further my Buſineſs; <hi>Elys</hi> laſt Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to me was in theſe Words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I <hi>Do not love to add Affliction to Affliction, and yet I cannot but wonder that you ſhould ſeek to me either for Relief or Bayl, after ſuch a Requital of my good Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Civilities, both in Relation to his Majeſty and my ſelf, you have made it ſo dangerous to have any thing to do with you, that common Diſcretion obliges me to keep my Diſtance, even againſt my inclinations to a Work of Charity; for I do pitty your Condition, but to ſend you any ſort of Supply, would look as if I were afraid of you, or intended to make uſe of you, but my Integrity hath kept me out of your Power, and as to any manner of Correſpondence I have done with you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Only this I think I might ſecurely do for you,</hi> Monſieur Choqueux <hi>was lamenting the ill ſtate of your Health, and I moved him to take ſome care of you, that way, but his Anſwer was that he did not know what Conſtruction might be made of it, but I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that if you ſhould write to him ſuch a Letter, as might ſecure him from being miſinterpreted, by ſome acknowledgment of what he hath already done for you, and ſuch Declarations under your Hand as might be an Evidence that it was at your own Inſtance, and only in Order to your Recovery, I do not know I ſay but you might prevail with him, to go on with your Cure; Conſider the goodneſs of God to you, to give you time to repent of your Wickedneſs, and ſet about it ſeriouſly, in which good Deſign God aſſiſt you through the Mercies of Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>September <hi>25th</hi> 1680, 7 at Night.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>Farewel,</salute>
                     <signed>S. ELY.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64123:9"/>
After I had received this Letter of <hi>Elys,</hi> Captain <hi>Richardſon</hi> ſent for me, and ſaid he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed that ſeveral Perſons had been to ſpeak with me, I told him Colonel <hi>Manſel,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſon had been with me, and likewiſe ſome Catholiques, and then he bid me fetch my Linnen, and removed me out of the Preſs-yard into the Maſter-ſide Debtors; from whence I was ordered to appear the ſecond time before the Lords of his Majeſties moſt honourable Privy Councel; his Majeſty being then likewiſe preſent; where my Affidavit which was taken upon Oath before Mr. Juſtice <hi>Bridgeman</hi> being read, and the Lords were then many of Opinion, that <hi>Ely</hi> was the main Perſon, which did inſtigate me to draw up thoſe Objections againſt the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Plot; this Account being more large than the Affidavit, not having then ſo much time to recollect my Memory, ſo fully as I have ſince done; and this I have performed with all due Reſpect to the Perſons concerned, without clamorous and abuſive Reflections; and with Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Truth, without wronging any Perſon in the Relation, and though <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> has ſo groſly abuſed me in his lying and ſcandalous Dialogue, yet I only plainly lay down the matter of Fact; and the ſeveral Intrigues and Diſcourſes that paſt betwixt us, and as near as I could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the very Words, and leave it freely to the Judgment of any unbiaſt Perſon; whether <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> be ſo innocent, or made ſo ſlight a matter of what I ſaid to him, as he publiſhes in his Caſe, inſerting in it what he pleaſes, and many times mentioning Perſons with us, when there were none, which is but a ſmall Fault, but he confounds the whole Series of the Diſcourſe which I had with him; as is ſufficiently evident and perſpicuous to any Perſon that will be at ſo much Pains, as to compare my Account with his Dialogue; and though he may have more Wit, I am ſure he has not ſo much Honeſty in the Relation.</p>
            <p>Since I was committed to <hi>Newgate,</hi> the laſt Term a <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> was brought for me, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> where I moved my Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Scroggs,</hi> that I might be removed to the <hi>Kings Bench;</hi> and upon my motion to the Judges I was committed to the Priſon of the Court; And no farther ſaith,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Simſon Tonge.</signed>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <head>Witneſs.</head>
                     <item>Thomas Waller.</item>
                     <item>John Rawlins.</item>
                     <item>Francis Ramme.</item>
                     <item>Thomas Castell.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
